# FELIPE TAHA SANT'ANA, Ph.D.

+48-882-844-704 | ftahas@proton.me | ftahas.github.io

in ftsantana | 🖸 ftahas | 🎔 ftsantan | 📵 ORCID | G Scholar

# Introduction

I am a theoretical physicist with experience in academia and a background on interacting quantum systems, integrable models, quantum field theories, mathematical physics, and AMO physics in general. I am currently a Polonez Bis fellow at Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, working on integrable quantum field theories under the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality.

#### **EDUCATION**

• University of São Paulo

04/2020

Ph.D. in Physics

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Bose gases, optical lattice, quantum phase transition, 1d interacting systems.
- Thesis: A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas. arXiv:2006.13100; teses.usp

University of São Paulo

07/2015

M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Autonomous robots, dynamical environments, collision probability estimation.
- · Dissertation: Estimação de probabilidade de colisão com obstáculos móveis para navegação autônoma. teses.usp

#### University of São Paulo

07/2012

B.Sc. in Physics São Carlos, Brazil

#### EXPERIENCE

# Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences [ ]

11/2022 - 10/2024

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

- NCN Polonez Bis 1 Fellow
- Principal Investigator of the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality

# • Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw [

10/2020 - 09/2022

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

- Postdoctoral researcher within the NCN Sonata project "Dynamic correlation functions of quantum integrable models: in and beyond the equilibrium" headed by Miłosz Panfil.
- Institut de Physique de Nice, Universit
  è Côte D'Azur [ ]

06/2018 - 05/2019

Ph.D. Researcher

Nice, France

- Doctoral researcher under CAPES/COFECUB bilateral collaboration.
- São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paulo [ ]

04/2016 - 04/2020

Ph.D. Researcher

São Carlos, Brazil

- Doctoral researcher within project "Bose gases in optical lattices" headed by F.E.A. dos Santos.
- Luz Financial Solutions [ ]

2015

Financial Analyst

São Carlos, Brazil

São Carlos School of Engineering [ )

03/2013-07/2015

M.Sc. Researcher

São Carlos, Brazil

- Master student within the project "Dynamic environments in autonomous robotics" headed by Valdir Grassi Jr.
- Warthog Robotics [\( \phi \)]

2012-2013

AI Developer

São Carlos, Brazil

### **TEACHING**

Quantum Field Theory

2023-2024

Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences

Warsaw, Poland

• Lecture notes

• Statistical Physics

2021-2022

Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw

Warsaw, Poland 2021-2022

Quantum Mechanics

Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw

Warsaw, Poland

Computational Physics

2017

São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paylo

São Carlos, Brazil

### **PROJECTS**

- CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality November 2022 October 2024 Keywords: Quantum Field Theories, Integrable models, 1d interacting systems
  - Project No. 2021/43/P/ST2/02904 co-funded by the National Science Centre and the European Union Framework Programme for Research and Innovation Horizon 2020 under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement no. 945339.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

C=CONFERENCE, J=JOURNAL, P=PATENT, S=IN SUBMISSION, T=THESIS

- [J.1] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Kubo-Martin-Schwinger relation for an interacting mobile impurity, Phys. Rev. Research 5, 043265, 2023. arXiv:2308.06482
- [J.2] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Mobile impurity in a one-dimensional gas at finite temperatures, Phys. Rev. A 106, 023305, 2022. arXiv:2202.07657
- [J.3] Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model, J. Stat. Mech. (2021) 073103. arXiv:2104.10491
- [T.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas, University of São Paulo thesis repository arXiv:2006.13100
- [J.4] F. T. Sant'Ana, F. Hébert, V. Rousseau, M. Albert, P. Vignolo, Scaling properties of Tan's contact: Embedding pairs and correlation effect in the Tonks-Girardeau limit, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 063608 (2019). arXiv:1908.08714
- [J.5] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Axel Pelster, and Francisco Ednilson Alves dos Santos, Finite-temperature degenerate pergutbation theory for bosons in optical lattices, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 043609 (2019). arXiv:1906.09661
- [J.6] M. Kübler, F. T. Sant'Ana, F. E. A. dos Santos, and A. Pelster, Improving mean-field theory for bosons in optical lattices via degenerate perturbation theory, *Phys. Rev. A* **99**, 063603 (2019).arXiv:1804.08689
- [C.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana et al., Warthog Robotics Team Description Paper 2012, Latin American Robotics Competition Symposium (2012).

# TALKS AND POSTERS

|   | 10 11 1 2022        |
|---|---------------------|
| Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in one dimension                         | 10-14 July 2023     |
| International Conference on Statistical Physics - SIGMAPHI 2023, Chania, Greece             |                     |
| Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in reduced dimensionality                | December 2022       |
| BEC seminar, CFT PAN, Warsaw, Poland  |                     |
| • The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model              | 20/02 - 04/03, 2022 |
| São Paulo School of Advanced Science on Quantum Fluids and Applications, São Carlos, Brazil |                     |
| Correlation features of interacting bosons  | October 2021        |
| Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland                                       |                     |
| Understanding the important excitations in the Lieb-Liniger model                           | April 2021          |
| Student workshop on integrability, 2021, Hannover, Germany                                  |                     |
| • A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the interacting Bose gas         | December 2020       |
| Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland                                       |                     |
| Bosons in optical lattices  | 30/01 - 10/02, 2017 |
| School on Interaction of Light with Cold Atoms, São Paulo, Brazil                           |                     |

## **S**KILLS

- Programming Languages: Fortran, C++, Python, HTML, Julia
- Systems and softwares: Linux, LaTeX, Mathematica, MatLab
- Languages: Portuguese (Native), English (Professional Proficiency), Spanish (Intermediate), Polish (Basic)